Alexander Buriticá Casanova

Contact information

E-mail: a.buritica@uniandes.edu.co

Webpage: https://alexanderburitica.github.io/

Summary

Economist and Ph.D. in economics with more than seven years of experience analyzing and impacting public policies in agriculture, technology adoption, and market access. I have demonstrated the ability to work with multidisciplinary and interinstitutional operational activities. From my work experience, I have acquired competencies such as organization skills, attention to detail, creativity, the ability to adapt to tight deadlines, and the ability to perform different functions.

Education

2016 – 2023 Universidad de los Andes – Bogotá, Colombia

Ph.D. in Economics

2016 - 2023 Universidad de los Andes - Bogotá, Colombia

M.Sc. in Economics

2007 – 2013 Universidad del Valle – Santiago de Cali, Colombia

B.Sc. in Economics

Professional Experience

2022 - Present Alliance of Bioversity International and CIAT) (Postdoctoral Fellow) -

Palmira, Colombia.

Main Activities:

 Leading Coordination and implementation of research activities in the project "Climate-smart initiatives for climate change adaptation and sustainability in prioritized agricultural production systems in Colombia" (CSICAP)

Alexander Buriticá

- Leading Coordination and implementation of research activities National Policies and Strategies for Food, Land and Water Systems Transformation. Work package two in Colombia. Coherence analysis.
- Providing support and collaboration in designing and implementing protocols, reports, and analyses for the impact and evaluation of ongoing projects.

Alliance of Bioversity International and CIAT) (Senior Research Associate) – Palmira, Colombia.

2022 - 2023

Main Activities:

- Coordination and implementation of research activities National Policies and Strategies for Food, Land and Water Systems Transformation. Work package two in Colombia. Coherence analysis.
- Support and collaboration in designing and implementing protocols, reports, and analysis for impact and evaluation of ongoing projects.

Verite (Development Economics Specialist) - Amherst, United States.

2021 - 2022

2019 - 2021

Main Activities:

- Coordination and implementation of a study on times and movements for coffee harvesting in Antioquia- Colombia.
- Coordination and implementation of a study on Living Wage-Living Income for coffee growers in the departments of Huila and Antioquia-Colombia.
- Leader in designing and implementing the monitoring system for the COFFEE pilot project -Colombia.
- Leader in the design and implementation of the impact evaluation of different alternative payment methods for coffee harvesters in Colombia.

International Center for Tropical Agriculture (CIAT) (Visiting Researcher) – Palmira, Colombia.

Main Activities:

- Fieldwork implementation and supervision, from interviewer training to quality control, for the baseline data collection of the MOCCA (Maximizing Opportunities in Coffee and Cocoa in the Americas) project funded by TechnoServe-USDA.
- Participation in the analysis and preparation of baseline reports for the seven countries (Peru, Ecuador, Nicaragua, Honduras, El Salvador, and Guatemala) involved in the MOCCA project. Provide recommendations to project partners for intervention prioritization to improve productivity and producer welfare based on economic analysis.

Alexander Buriticá

2013 - 2016

 Co-author of academic publications journals. In charge of the economic evaluation of silvopastoral systems adoption in Caquetá. Based on SAL (Sustainable Amazonian Landscapes) project training.

International Center for Tropical Agriculture (CIAT) (Research Assistant) – Palmira, Colombia .

Main Activities:

- Coordination design and implementation of fieldwork for the baseline and end-line of the "Borderlands Coffee Project: Improving Income and Employment Opportunities among Coffee Farmers and the Displaced of Colombia and Ecuador.
- Implementation of focus groups on coffee production cost in eight municipalities of Narino-Colombia.
- Impact assessment of the Borderlands Coffee Project- Colombia.
- Coordination design and implementation of fieldwork for the "Coffee and Climate Change- Nicaragua" project. Information was collected from 1,000 coffee households in the central coffee-growing regions of the country.
- Responsible for generating economic and econometric analyses to evaluate the relationship between ecosystem services and food security in indigenous communities of the Amazon in Colombia and Perú.
- Economic analysis of improved rice varieties adoption in Latin America. Study based on information from workshops held with Nicaragua, Peru, Venezuela, Costa Rica, Bolivia, and Panama experts.

Other skills, courses, awards

Software

LATEX, R, STATA, ARCGIS

Idiomas

Ingles (Avanzado), Español (materno)

Courses

- 2019. EGAP Learning Days. The focus of the workshop is on experimental methods. Bogotá, Colombia. *Organized by Universidad de los Andes*.
- 2015. Training workshop on Evaluation of Adoption and Impact Economic of Agricultural Technologies. Palmira, Colombia. *Organized by CIAT and Michigan State University*.
- 2013. R Training using Impact lite data sets. Nairobi, Kenia. *International Livestock Research Institute*.

Alexander Buriticá

Awards

2019. ICO Award for Excellence in Coffe-Related Research. London, United Kingdom.International Coffee Organization (ICO). This Award aims to promote high-quality research on emerging issues in the global coffee sector. Paper: Access to High Quality Coffee Markets: Possible for All?".

2017. Doctoral Scholarship. COLCIENCIAS. The Colombian department of Science and Technology offers this scholarship to support Colombians in their doctoral studies.

Publications

- The risk of unintended deforestation from scaling sustainable livestock production systems . Castro-Nunez, A., Buriticá, C. Gonzalez, E. Villarino, F. Holmann, L. Perez, M. Del Río, D. Sandoval, L. Eufemia, K. Löhr, S. Durango, M. Romero, M. Lana, S. Sotelo, O. Rivera, A. Loboguerrero, M. Quintero.

 Conservation Science and Practice, e495.
- 2017 Land related grievances shape tropical forest-cover in areas affected by armed-conflict. Castro-Nunez, O Mertz, A Buritica, CC Sosa, ST Lee.

 Applied Geography 85, 39-50.
- Identifying Socioeconomic Characteristics Defining Consumers'Acceptance for Main Organoleptic Attributes of an Iron-biofortified Bean Variety in Guatemala .S P´erez, A Buritica, A Oparinde, E Birol, C Gonzalez, M Zeller.

 International Journal on Food System Dynamics 8 (3), 222-235.
- 2017 Gestión Ambiental y Gobernanza Ambiental en los Municipios del Valle del Cauca A Buritica, F Arias.

 Ambiente y Sostenibilidad 5, 78-96..
- The effect of specialty coffee certification on household livelihood strategies and specialisation. W Vellema, AB Casanova, C Gonzalez, M D'Haese. Food Policy 57, 13-25.